hello hi gotham uh my name is simon and
i'm going to show you in just 10 minutes
how to build test and publish
an open source python library
um i'm actually going to publish a library while
i record this talk and this is a piece of code
which i've been copying and pasting into projects
for over a decade now it's a very simple little
thing that helps you create string based um
shortened versions of numeric identifiers
i'll do a quick demonstration of what that looks
like um let's paste it into a jupiter notebook
and now if i do pid.fromint one two three four it
says gxd and if i do pid.2 int of gxd it says one
two three four so very simple piece of code let's
turn this into a package on the python package um
on the python package index so i'm going to create
a directory called pids i checked and this is a an
available name right now and i'm going to add that
file um let's create a new file called headstockpi
we'll stick it in that folder and we'll paste
in that code so there's my code um creating a
package all you need for sure is a setup.pie
file which describes how the package will work
so i'm going to create that and then i'm going
to paste in this little template here this is the
simplest possible version of a valid setup.my file
i'm going to give it the name pids version 0.1
it's a tiny python library in the description
and the only module i'm going to include is
that pid stop by file i just created so now in
here we have two files pit stop pi and setup.pi
now if i run python3 setup.pi sdist this is where
the magic happens that command there created me a
file called pids hyphen 0.1.gz and that is a
file which i can install into any environment
to install this package i can actually demonstrate
that once again in this um jupyter notebook let's
pop that open and we'll do pip install what's
that what was it slash dist slash um there we go
when that prices it installs it and now if i
type import pids i have pids.pid as a piece of
code that i can start to run so let's upload this
to the python package index the way we do that is
with a tool called twine i can say twine upload
dist and then pass it the name of that file that
i've just created when i do this it'll ask me to
log in with my username and my pi pi password so
you'll need to create an account on pi pi before
you do this i do that it shows me the upload
and it gives me a url and this is live on the
internet right now this is now package which
anyone in the world can install by running pip
install pids but you'll notice it says here the
author of this package has not provided
a project description we're missing our
documentation so let's build that now as a simple
readme that we can add into that package so here's
a tiny bit of documentation i wrote earlier i'm
going to save that in a file called readme.md
and vs code can give us a little preview of it
showing you what that looks like it's not very
exciting but it does explain what's going on
so now we need to bundle that into our overall
package the way we do that is by adding a tiny bit
more of a recipe to our setup.pi file um here we
go i'll copy and paste this in so we can add two
more arguments here um there's description long
description and long description content type
and here we're doing we're calling a function
i've written called get long description which
reads that readme file on disk and puts that in a
variable so we add this little bit of boilerplate
and we set that as the long description um i'm
going to bump up the version number to 0.1.1 to
reflect that change and now once again we can
run python3 setup.pi sdist um oh it doesn't like
that because i forgot the import os there can do
that we now have a file in dist called 0.1.1 and
again if we do twine upload dist slash pids 1.1
and stick in those credentials one more time
this has given us our second base on pipe
ui and this release is it's improved it's
got documentation the contents of that
readme is now available for people to see
so for our next step let's add some tests i'm
going to need a tiny bit more boilerplate for
this i need to add pi test as a test dependency
so i'll paste this in here this is saying that
the pids test dependencies are my test and now
i'm going to create myself a python virtual
environment i'll call it vien i'll do source via
flash bin activate it to activate it and i'm going
to type pimp install dash e for editable of my
current directory and its test dependencies so
running this installs pi test now if i run pi test
it runs my tests except i don't have any tests yet
so let's create a test folder and i'm going to
create a file in that called test underscore pids
in stockpi and the great thing about pi test is
that tests are really really small smart shorts so
we could say test from int and it's
going to say assertpids.pid.fromint1234
equals and mzq so i'll try running that test
and it fails because i got it wrong it's gxd
is the correct value i can stick gxd in
and now my test passes i'll do that in
the opposite direction so i'll test test to int i
test that two int of gxd equals one two three four
and when those tests there one two three five
gx fgxd that's why there we go and so now i
have a pasting passing test suite and this can
obviously be extended to be a lot more thorough
so the next step is to get this up on github
i'm going to create a new github repo called
pids i'll use the default settings for that
and then a handy thing about github is it
just gives you the commands you need to run
for you to copy and paste in so i'll do that
i'm going to git add my readme my
pids.pie my setup.pi and that test as well
and then i'll paste in these four lines here and
that will go ahead and create that repository for
me but the really neat thing about github
these days is you can use github actions
to run your tests for you um the way you do that
is be by creating a github workflows directory
so rather than create that um by hand i'm going
to copy that from a project i worked on recently
um my sqlite explain project i happen to know has
one of these and i'm going to copy that folder
here so now if we look in here we now
have a github folder with a publish
um yaml and a test yaml this right here is the one
we're going to try out first what this does is it
installs the package under four different versions
of python runs and runs those tests for us
so i can now do the git add dot
github git commit github actions
get push and over here github will spot that
the those actions have been configured and
start running that test action for me straight
away you can see this actually turns into four
different jobs in github actions one for each of
those versions of python that we are targeting
and it's already started running those it's
running them in parallel for all different four
versions all four different versions we look
at this one here it's um set up some caching
it's called it's installed dependencies it's run
the tests and they've passed and we can see the
green ticks clicking in and just like that our
tests have been run on four versions of python
and our commit that even gets a little
green tick to show what had happened
so i have one last trick up my sleeve i'm going
to push a new release directly from github and
without running anything on my computer at all
where i'm going to do this is by creating a
api token on pipi called pids i'm going to
give it the scope of being able to publish
to that pids project and that token and i will
copy this token and then paste it into the secrets
for my github repository so i can do add secret
um call it pypi token and paste it in here and now
anytime i push a release to this github
repository my um publish workflow will run
and will publish that release so i'm going to
modify my version number let's call this 0.1.2
and i'm going to publish a new release um release
it's create new release it's going to be called
0.1.2 and let's just say added added tests will
stop i hit the publish button and once again that
action kicks into effect so this is my publish
python package action which is running the tests
first because you wouldn't want to publish a
package if you haven't thoroughly tested it
and once the tests have passed it fires
up a deploy action which runs that twine
upload script that i showed you earlier so this
right here is installing the required packages
and now it's publishing that package up to pipi
that's done and here is a package on pipeli
that was published entirely through automation
using github actions so thanks for listening
and i have published extensive notes on this at
github.com simon w pi gotham hyphen packaging